<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="create-passive-vpn-vpc">
  <title>Creating a VPN Connection</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT; provides you with the ability to establish a site-to-site VPN connection between
    &PRODUCT; virtual routers. To achieve that, add a passive mode Site-to-Site VPN. With this
    functionality, users can deploy applications in multiple Availability Zones or VPCs, which can
    communicate with each other by using a secure Site-to-Site VPN Tunnel.</para>
  <para>This feature is supported on all the hypervisors.</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Create two VPCs. For example, VPC A and VPC B.</para>
      <para>For more information, see <xref linkend="configure-vpc"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Create VPN gateways on both the VPCs you created.</para>
      <para>For more information, see <xref linkend="create-vpn-gateway-for-vpc"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Create VPN customer gateway for both the VPCs.</para>
      <para>For more information, see <xref linkend="create-vpn-customer-gateway"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Enable a VPN connection on VPC A in passive mode. </para>
      <para>For more information, see <xref linkend="create-vpn-connection-vpc"/>.</para>
      <para>Ensure that the customer gateway is pointed to VPC B. The VPN connection is shown in the
        Disconnected state.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Enable a VPN connection on VPC B. </para>
      <para>Ensure that the customer gateway is pointed to VPC A.  Because virtual router of VPC A,
        in this case, is in passive mode and is waiting for the virtual router of VPC B to initiate
        the connection, VPC B virtual router should not be in passive mode. </para>
      <para>The VPN connection is shown in the Disconnected state. </para>
      <para>Creating VPN connection on both the VPCs initiates a VPN connection. Wait for few seconds. The default is 30 seconds for both the VPN connections to show the Connected state.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</section>
