<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
            or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
            distributed with this work for additional information
            regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
            to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
            "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
            with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
            
            http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
            
            Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
            software distributed under the License is distributed on an
            "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
            KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
            specific language governing permissions and limitations
            under the License.
-->	
<section id="creating-compute-offerings">
    <title>Creating a New Compute Offering</title>
    <para>To create a new compute offering:</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>Log in with admin privileges to the &PRODUCT; UI.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>In the left navigation bar, click Service Offerings.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>In Select Offering, choose Compute Offering.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Click Add Compute Offering.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>In the dialog, make the following choices:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: Any desired name for the service offering.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: A short description of the offering that can be
                        displayed to users</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Storage type</emphasis>: The type of disk that should be allocated.
                        Local allocates from storage attached directly to the host where the system
                        VM is running. Shared allocates from storage accessible via NFS.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Custom</emphasis>: If checked, the end-user must fill in the desired values for
                number of CPU cores, CPU MHz, and Memory when creating a VM based on this offering.
                When you check this box, those three input fields are hidden in the dialog box.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold"># of CPU cores</emphasis>: The number of cores which should be allocated
                        to a system VM with this offering.
                        If Custom is checked, this field does not appear.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">CPU (in MHz)</emphasis>: The CPU speed of the cores that the system VM
                        is allocated. For example, “2000” would provide for a 2 GHz clock.
                        If Custom is checked, this field does not appear.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Memory (in MB)</emphasis>: The amount of memory in megabytes that the
                        system VM should be allocated. For example, “2048” would provide for a 2 GB
                        RAM allocation.
                        If Custom is checked, this field does not appear.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Network Rate</emphasis>: Allowed data transfer rate in MB per
                        second.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Disk Read Rate</emphasis>: Allowed disk read rate in bits per second.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Disk Write Rate</emphasis>: Allowed disk write rate in bits per second.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Disk Read Rate</emphasis>: Allowed disk read rate in IOPS (input/output operations per second).</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Disk Write Rate</emphasis>: Allowed disk write rate in IOPS  (input/output operations per second).</para></listitem>    
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Offer HA</emphasis>: If yes, the administrator can choose to have the
                        system VM be monitored and as highly available as possible.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Storage Tags</emphasis>: The tags that should be associated with the
                        primary storage used by the system VM.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Host Tags</emphasis>: (Optional) Any tags that you use to organize your
                        hosts</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">CPU cap</emphasis>: Whether to limit the level of CPU usage even if
                        spare capacity is available.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Public</emphasis>: Indicate whether the service offering should be
                        available all domains or only some domains. Choose Yes to make it available
                        to all domains. Choose No to limit the scope to a subdomain; &PRODUCT;
                        will then prompt for the subdomain's name.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">isVolatile</emphasis>: If checked, VMs created from this service
                        offering will have their root disks reset upon reboot. This is useful for
                        secure environments that need a fresh start on every boot and for desktops
                        that should not retain state.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Deployment Planner</emphasis>: Choose the technique that you would like &PRODUCT;
                to use when deploying VMs based on this service offering.</para>
                <para>First Fit places new VMs on the first host that is found having sufficient capacity to support the VM's requirements.</para>
                <para>User Dispersing makes the best effort to evenly distribute VMs belonging to the same account on different clusters or pods.</para>
                <para>User Concentrated prefers to deploy VMs belonging to the same account within a single pod.</para>
                <para>Implicit Dedication will deploy VMs on private infrastructure that is dedicated to a specific domain or account.
                  If you choose this planner, then you must also pick a value for Planner Mode.
                  <phrase condition="admin">See <xref linkend="dedicated-host-cluster-pod"/>.</phrase>
                  <phrase condition="install">See Dedicating Resources to Accounts and Domains in the Administration Guide.</phrase></para>
                <para>Bare Metal is used with bare metal hosts.
                    <phrase condition="admin">See Bare Metal Installation in the Installation Guide.</phrase>
                    <phrase condition="install">See <xref linkend="baremetal-install"/>.</phrase></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Planner Mode</emphasis>: Used when ImplicitDedicationPlanner is selected in the previous field.
              The planner mode determines how VMs will be deployed on private infrastructure that is dedicated to a single domain or account.</para>
              <para>Strict: A host will not be shared across multiple accounts. For example, strict implicit dedication is useful for deployment of certain types of applications, such as desktops, where no host can be shared between different accounts without violating the desktop software's terms of license.</para>
              <para>Preferred: The VM will be deployed in dedicated infrastructure if possible. Otherwise, the VM can be deployed in shared infrastructure.</para>
           </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></listitem> 
        <listitem><para>Click Add.</para></listitem>        
    </orderedlist>                
    
    
</section>
