<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->

<section id="secondary-storage-add">
	<title>Adding Secondary Storage</title>
    <note><para>Be sure there is nothing stored on the server. Adding the server to &PRODUCT; will destroy any existing data.</para></note>
    <para/>
    <para>When you create a new zone, the first secondary storage is added as part of that procedure. You can add secondary storage servers at any time to add more servers to an existing zone.</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>To prepare for the zone-based Secondary Staging Store, you should have created and mounted an NFS share during Management Server installation.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Make sure you prepared the system VM template during Management Server installation.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI as root administrator.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>In the left navigation bar, click Infrastructure.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>In Secondary Storage, click View All.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Click Add Secondary Storage.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Fill in the following fields:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: Give the storage a descriptive name.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Provider</emphasis>: Choose the type of storage provider (such as S3,
            Swift, or NFS). NFS can be used for zone-based storage, and the others for region-wide
            object storage. Depending on which provider you choose, additional fields will appear.
            Fill in all the required fields for your selected provider. For more information,
            consult the provider's documentation (such as the S3 or Swift website). </para>
          <para>For Hyper-V, select SMB/CIFS.</para>
                <warning><para>You can use only a single region-wide object storage account per region.
                For example, you can not mix both Swift and S3, or use S3 accounts from multiple different users.</para></warning><para/></listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Create NFS Secondary Staging Store</emphasis>: Be sure this box is
            checked, unless the zone already contains a secondary staging store. This would only be
            the case if you are upgrading an existing NFS secondary storage into an object storage,
            as described in <phrase condition="install"><xref linkend="upgrading-to-object-storage"
              />.</phrase>
            <phrase condition="admin">Upgrading from NFS to Object Storage in the Installation
              Guide.</phrase> In this case, you can skip the rest of the fields described below
            (Zone, NFS Server, and Path).</para>
                <warning><para>If you are setting up a new zone, be sure the box is checked.
                    This checkbox and the three fields below it must be filled in.
                    Even when object storage (such as S3) is used as the secondary storage provider, an NFS
                    staging storage in each zone is still required.</para></warning><para/></listitem>
                <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Zone</emphasis>: The zone where the NFS Secondary Staging
            Store is to be located.</para>
        </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Server.</emphasis> The IP address or DNS name of
                  the storage device.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Path.</emphasis> The exported path from the
                  server.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">SMB Username</emphasis>: Applicable only if you select
            SMB/CIFS provider. The username of the account which has the necessary permissions to
            the SMB shares. The user must be part of the Hyper-V administrator group.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">SMB Password</emphasis>: Applicable only if you select
            SMB/CIFS provider. The password associated with the account.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">SMB Domain</emphasis>: Applicable only if you select
            SMB/CIFS provider. The Active Directory domain that the SMB share is a part of.</para>
              </listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">NFS server</emphasis>: The name of the zone's Secondary Staging
            Store.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis>: The path to the zone's Secondary Staging Store.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <section id="secondary-staging-store">
        <title>Adding an NFS Secondary Staging Store for Each Zone</title>
        <para>You can skip this section if you are upgrading an existing zone from NFS to object storage.
          You only need to perform the steps below when setting up a new zone that does not yet have its NFS server.</para>
        <para>Every zone must have at least one NFS store provisioned; multiple NFS servers are
            allowed per zone. To provision an NFS Staging Store for a zone:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem><para>To prepare for the zone-based Secondary Staging Store, you should have created and mounted an NFS share during Management Server installation.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Make sure you prepared the system VM template during Management Server installation.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI as root administrator.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>In the left navigation bar, click Infrastructure.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>In Secondary Storage, click View All.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>In Select View, choose Secondary Staging Store.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Click the Add NFS Secondary Staging Store button.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Fill out the dialog box fields, then click OK:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>Zone. The zone where the NFS Secondary Staging Store is to be located.</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>NFS server. The name of the zone's Secondary Staging Store.</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Path. The path to the zone's Secondary Staging Store.</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
  <xi:include href="s3-ss-add.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</section>
